A Guide to the Papers of Notable Virginia Families, 1763-1866
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Lewis Family Papers
  - 1825-1834, n.d. (Box 2)
    early letters until his marriage in 1827 were written from Philadelphia, where he was being educated; discusses the conflict in Philadelphia over the election for President (1825 February 3); the unsuccessful attempt of John Peter to purchase slaves in Philadelphia due to lack of proper power of attorney (1825 December 13); concern over the condition of the plantation "Audley" (1825 December 27); instructions to his father for repairs and painting to be done at "Audley" at Battletown because of his upcoming marriage to Esther Maria Coxe (1804-1885) of Philadelphia (1827 April 25, August 25); his mare, Belinda, has produced an uncommonly fine colt, his need for a cook, and the sale of family slaves (1831 April 28); refers to wages of the emancipated slaves from the George Washington estate (1832 July 19); record of the account of money sent to Lewis by Allen Williams (1833 July 5); description of harvesting his wheat (n.y. July 18); the majority of his letters are of a personal nature and discuss activities at his estate "Audley".
  - Robert Lewis (1769-1828) to his brother, Lawrence Lewis 1804-1828 (Box 2)
    His letters generally concern financial matters but also: the breaking of the engagement of Nancy Lewis and the estate of George Washington (1804 January 8); his purchase of the Hunter estate in Frederick County, Virginia (1804 March 17); made captain of the Washington Volunteer Company of Artillery and Infantry, created after the Chesapeake and Leopard affair took place, and mentions the Embargo and possibility of war (1807 December 24); the death of his youngest daughter and concern over incursions by the British forced a move to Stafford County(1814 September 9); the estates of brother Fielding Lewis and George Lewis (1822 March 22); the death of their brother-in-law, Charles Carter (1827 May 20); a check for Betty Carter and the sale of medals belonging formerly to the George Washington estate to Daniel Webster (1827 December 22); and the recovery of his daughter Betty (1828 January 17).
  - Samuel Lewis to Warner W. Lewis 1814 August 23 (Box 2)
    The estate of George Washington.
  - Warner W. Lewis to Lawrence Lewis 1801-1814 (Box 2)
    Informs him about the taxes on his western lands (1801 December 4); asks about the lands on Rough Creek (1810 January 22); doubts the wisdom of the Cabinet in siphoning off too many American soldiers during the War of 1812 to take Canada when they were needed at home for defense against the enemy (1814 August 21).
  - George Mason to Lawrence Lewis 1826 November 8 (Box 2)
    Asks to exchange sixty or seventy bushels of wheat.
  - John Mason to Lawrence Lewis 1824 April 18 (Box 2)
    discusses the price of a slave, William, and his wife.
  - Dr. R.C. Mason to Lawrence Lewis 1817 and 1835 (Box 2)
    discusses the sale of a slave.
  - Rev. Edward Charles McGuire (1793-1858) to Lawrence Lewis 1839 February 5 (Box 2)
    Urges a speedy settlement of the estate of his father-in-law, Robert Lewis, rather than waiting on the outcome of a suit pending before the Supreme Court.
  - John Milton to Lawrence Lewis 1810 January 10 (Box 2)
    Writes concerning the settlement of accounts of Lewis in Battletown, Clark County, Virginia.
  - 1813 (Box 2)
    discusses the price of wool and the difficulties of the wool industry.
  - Andrew Parke to Lawrence Lewis 1813 September 16 (Box 2)
    Attempts to locate a source for salt and to produce it for sale, and the use of salt pans versus cast [iron?] kettles to boil away the water.
  - 1830 (Box 2)
    discusses the estate of George Washington and the sale of the mare, Belinda.
  - Joseph Prentis to Lorenzo Lewis 1840 and 1843 (Box 2)
    Writes concerning the estate of George Washington and the Dismal Swamp land.
  - Robert Pollard to Lawrence Lewis 1831 December 9 (Box 2)
    His daughter, Ellen Lewis, wife of Howell Lewis, is in Richmond investigating the interests of the family in the shares of the Loyal Company.
  - Matthew Ranson to Lawrence Lewis 1819-1826 (Box 2)
    discusses his payments towards the purchase of the Rock Hall estate, five miles from Charles Town, in Jefferson County, [West] Virginia.
  - Alexander Spotswood to Lawrence Lewis 1803 March 16 (Box 2)
    discusses business.
  - F.D. Stone to Lawrence Lewis 1825 October 10 (Box 2)
    discusses the estate of the late Dr. Daniel Jenifer of St. Thomas.
  - George Tucker to Lawrence Lewis 1806 and 1822 (Box 2)
    A University of Virginia professor who married the niece of Lewis, Maria Bell Carter (1784-1823), mentions the accident suffered by his son, George (1806 February 27) and the sale of a slave, Billy (1822 July 8).
  - Henry St. George Tucker to Lawrence Lewis 1817 October 29 (Box 2)
    Gives advice concerning his suit in [Battletown?.
  - Obed Waite to Lorenzo Lewis and Lawrence Lewis 1830 and 1832 (Box 2)
    discusses the suit of Lawrence Lewis in Berkeley County against Mr. Taylor.
  - Samuel T. Washington (1800-1874) to Lawrence Lewis 1831-1832 (Box 2)
    Writes concerning the death of his father, Captain Samuel Washington (1765-1831), (1831 August 28); the estate of George Washington and the claim of Mrs. [Mildred Washington?] Hammond (1832 April 24; June 30; July 12; September 20).
  - William Temple Washington (1800-1874) to Lawrence Lewis 1832-1833 (Box 2)
    Son of George Steptoe Washington, concerning the the estate of George Washington.
  - James Webb to Lawrence Lewis 1796 March 10 (Box 2)
    concerning payment of his bond.
  - Allen Williams to Lawrence Lewis 1832 June 28 (Box 2)
    concerning payment of interest to Lewis.
  - Financial Documents, including Elias Langham, Henry Ashburn, and William Ferguson 1801-1818 (Box 2)
    [pertaining to the estate of George Washington and shoes provided for "free Negroes," emancipated slaves from the George Washington estate]
- Madison Family Papers
  - Correspondence
    - John Anderson to his wife, Mrs. Alice Anderson 1813 August 19 (Box 2)
      Briefly mentions a great force of the enemy, as well as the American forces, at Annapolis, Maryland, and their expectation of an imminent attack.
    - Augustus, Count of Wurttemberg (1813-1885), to Dolley Madison 1844 January 20 (Box 2)
      Requests an autograph of James Madison for the National Institute of the Kingdom of Wurttemberg, Germany.
    - Richard Bache to James Madison n.y. June 4 (Box 2)
      Has paid a draft of John Payne Todd's for three hundred dollars, to prevent his arrest and imprisonment, and asks the Madisons to reimburse him for that amount.
    - Mary Charlotte Anne Bagot to Dolley Madison [1816] and 1818 (Box 2)
      Mourning for the death of Lady Bagot, prevents her and her husband from attending the gathering at the drawing room of the Madisons.
    - Miss Clara Baldwin to Dolley Madison 1813 February 16 (Box 2)
      Sister of Ruth Barlow, writes concerning the mission of Joel Barlow (1754-1812) to negotiate with the Emperor Napoleon in Zarnavica, Poland, which ended in his death on December 14th, his deprivations on the journey, the incompetence and misconduct of David Bailie Warden (1797-1845) towards Barlow, while in Paris, and who, after Barlow's death, demanded the United States seal from the widow and acted with French approval as if he were the United States minister; her concern with the lack of security for the official dispatches and the cyphers.
    - Frances C. Barbour to Dolley Madison n.y. September 27 (Box 2)
      Writing on mourning papers, she sends a specimen of grapes, a pink sachet made by herself, and her best wishes.
    - James Barbour (1775-1842)to James Madison 1828 June 11 (Box 2)
      Regrets that they will not be able to come by to say their farewells but hopes to see them at Barboursville.
    - Ruth Baldwin Barlow to Dolley Madison 1812 November 25 (Box 2)
      Ruth Baldwin Barlow (1755-1818) writes concerning the mission of her husband, Joel Barlow (1754-1812), United States minister to France, to negotiate with the Emperor Napoleon in Zarnavica, Poland, where he died on December 14th shortly after this letter was written; she also asks for the Madisons to remember the distress of the Marquis St. Simon and his daughter, both in prison (1812 November 25).
    - John Strode Barbour (1790-1855) to Dolley Madison 1844 March 26 (Box 2)
      In a meeting with several Virginia and Alabama members of Congress, he found them all favorable to Mrs. Madison's request and recommends Mr. Rives as a "safe, discreet, and sincere" counselor.
    - John Barnes to James Madison 1799 May 18 (Box 2)
      Informs Madison that General Stephen Moylan (1737-1811) has paid the order upon made him.
    - [Odilon Barrott to Robert Chilton] n.d., Envelope only (Box 2)
    - William Wallace Smith Bliss, private secretary and son-in-law to President Taylor, to John Payne Todd 1849 May 7 (Box 2)
      Refuses Todd's offer of the portraits of the early Presidents for the White House as an improper use of the furnishing fund appropriated by Congress.
    - Robert Brent (1764-1819), paymaster of the United States Army, to Dolley Madison 1811 December 6 (Box 2)
      Writes concerning the draft of Colonel James Taylor.
    - John Campbell, Treasurer of the United States, to Dolley Madison 1837 March 20 (Box 2)
      Promises to attend to her request for the payment of $30,000 which was authorized by Congress.
    - Mary Caton to Dolley Madison 1838 February 6 (Box 2)
      Introduces the Countess Masterson and her niece Miss Masterson.
    - Reynolds Chapman, clerk of Orange County, Virginia, 1801-1844, to James Madison 1831 October 22 (Box 2)
      Writes concerning his mother's estate.
    - John Randolph Clay to Hugh Swinton Legare (1797-1843) 1833 June 29 (Box 2)
      Writes concerning the controversy over nullification and the tariff, the "[Virginia?]Resolutions of '98," the nomination of William John Duane as Secretary of the Treasury.
    - John Hartwell Cocke (1780-1866) to James Madison 1827 February 6 (Box 2)
      discusses the issues of hotel keepers and military instruction at the University of Virginia.
    - Maria K. Crittenden to Dolley Madison 1837 and 1838 (Box 2)
      discusses social occasions.
    - Joseph Ignacio DeViar to Dolley Madison 1801 May 20 (Box 2)
      Congratulations upon the appointment of James Madison as Secretary of State.
    - [Catharine Morgan] Dix to Annie [Payne] n.d. (Box 2)
      Promises her children will visit before they leave.
    - George Coke Dromgoole to Dolley Madison 1844 March 15 and June 19 (Box 2)
      Writes concerning the possible purchase or publication of Madison's works for the Library of Congress.
    - Samuel H. Eakin to James Madison 1806 November 15 and 22 (Box 2)
      Furnishes the expenses involved with the shipment of two cases of china, from Nantes, France, to the United States.
    - F. Erskine to Dolley Madison Saturday, n.y. (Box 2)
      Sends two bottles of wine to Mrs. Madison.
    - Caroline Langdon Eustis to Dolley Madison 1815 May 11 (Box 2)
      Refers to her husband, William Eustis, his posting to Holland, and the delays in getting a ship there due to the uncertainty of international events; mentions the frigate Congress, and William Bainbridge, the superintendent of the construction of the Independence, their unfortunate little friend, Madam Bonaparte, and the impropriety in her accompanying the Eustis' on their trip to Holland due to the revolution in France, [the Hundred Days return of Napoleon?.
    - William Eustis (1753-1825), Secretary of War, to Dolley Madison 1811 April 10 (Box 2)
      Discusses appointments of the "officers of the Legion".
    - Ferdinando Fairfax (1766-1820) to James Madison 1806 November 8 (Box 2)
      Asks if the Postmaster General can answer the enclosed questions concerning the routes, and the times of the arrival and departure of the post at Hagerstown, Winchester, Staunton, Washington, and Clarksburg.
    - Philip R. Fendall to Christopher Richmond 1788 June 19 (Box 2)
      Writes concerning a financial matter but mentions an upcoming vote by the Constitutional Convention on the nature of the proposed government.
    - John Murray Forbes (1771-1831) to James Madison 1801 July 21 (Box 2)
      Applies for a diplomatic position at Cadiz, Spain.
    - Richard Forrest, State Department clerk, to James Madison 1807 September 1 (Box 2)
      Offers himself for the diplomatic opening in the Mediterranean area.
    - John Forsyth (1780-1841) to Dolley Madison 1837 March 30 (Box 2)
      Writes concerning the purchase and future publication of Madison's works for the Library of Congress for $30,000.
    - Augustus John Foster (1780-1848), Secretary of the British Delegation, to James Madison 1807 September 20 (Box 2)
      Asks him to pick up a letter addressed to him at the Orange County Courthouse on his way to Washington.
    - John Fowler (1756-1840) to James Madison 1808 April 19 (Box 2)
      Writes concerning discounts paid on his note in the Bank of Columbia by General Mason.
    - Philip S. Fry (1801-1859), Orange County Court clerk, to John Payne Todd 1847-1851 (Box 2)
      Settlement of the debts of Dolley Madison and the suit of Henry W. Moncure against him.
    - Senator [John] Gaillard (1765-1826) to James Madison n.d. (Box 3)
      Cannot dine with the President tomorrow.
    - Joseph Gales (1786-1860), American Colonization Society, to John Payne Todd 1837 April 21 and May 3 (Box 3)
      Refers to receipts and a bank certificate.
    - Hannah (Nicholson) [Mrs. Albert] Gallatin to Dolley Madison 1813-1816 (Box 3)
      Refers to the recent illness of the President, her missing of her husband while absent on his mission to Russia to secure Russian mediation in the war with Great Britain (1813 August 15); her uneasiness over the delayed arrival of her husband and her hopes that Richard Bache will be made port master of Philadelphia (1814 January 14); furnishes an extract of her husband's letter dated Amsterdam, March 9th, which states they left Petersburg on January 25th and directed the captain of the Neptune to meet them at Amsterdam, but he was prevented by the severe winter weather, and she fears he has not heard of his new appointment as one of the peace commissioners to Great Britain, negotiating the Treaty of Ghent (1814 May 15 and August 9); her depression at not seeing her husband all year while he was on various missions to Europe on behalf of the United States (1814 December 26); discusses her furniture, the trials of Dolley Madison over the last six months, and hope of good news concerning the fate of New Orleans (1815 January 18); and her departure for Paris (1816 June 2).
    - Eliza (Johnson) Gilpin to Dolley Madison n.y. March 8 (Box 3)
      Asks when Mrs. A. Everett might conveniently visit her at home.
    - Alexander Hamilton, Jr. to James Madison 1811 March 28 (Box 3)
      Asks for a letter of introduction for use during his voyage to Europe.
    - R. Hamilton to Dolley Madison n.d. (Box 3)
      Sends shoes to Dolley.
    - Levett Harris to James Madison 1826 March 21 and October 21 (Box 3)
      Explains the origin and history of the indebtedness of John Payne Todd to himself and his attempts to secure payment, and asks Madison for help in securing recompense.
    - James Hoban to Dolley Madison 1844 November 21 (Box 3)
      Confers with her on a legal matter.
    - Dr. Robert Honeyman (1747-1824) to [Dolley Madison] 1797 December 28 (Box 3)
      Partial letter with instructions for making a medicine.
    - William Jarvis (1770-1859), Consul at Lisbon, to James Madison 1804 October 6 (Box 3)
      Sends articles for Dolley, listed in the letter, by way of the sloop Unity, commanded by Captain Deakins.
    - Thomas B. Johnson to James Madison 1808 March 10 (Box 3)
      Applied for the position of commissioner of the land office of the Louisiana Territory.
    - Walter Jones to Dolley Madison n.d. (Box 3)
      Tells her about the wreck of her carriage on the way back to town.
    - Representative William Jones (1760-1831) to James Madison 1801 July 22 and October 6 (Box 3)
      Forwards complaints made by the merchant, Chandler Price, of Philadelphia, concerning depredations made upon his property by British cruisers, and his own complaints as a partner in a mercantile house that recompense from the courts of Great Britain, when it occurs, is slow and not for the full value of the damages (1801 July 22); and an introduction to Robert Ritchie (October 6).
    - L. de Kantzow, wife of Baron Johan Albert de Kantzow, Stockholm, to Dolley Madison 1818 June 26 (Box 3)
      Recalling their acquaintance and her fond memories of being in the United States.
    - W.E. Kennaugh to John Payne Todd 1849 August 28 (Box 3)
      Writes concerning the circumstances surrounding the removal of the private papers of Dolley Madison from her residence at her death by Mrs. Cutts and Miss Payne, as reported to him by Dr. Thomas.
    - John W. Kinney to James Madison 1801 October 17 (Box 3)
      Offers himself for postmaster, should the position come open in Alexandria.
    - Thomas Law (1756-1834) to Dolley Madison n.d. (Box 3)
      Reports on the distribution of tickets to various luminaries; presents Mr. Bonchard's model of a mausoleum for George Washington; and invites her to solicit subscribers to a "translation" of maps by [Herve- Julien?] Le Sage
    - John Lee to James Madison 1801 July 27 (Box 3)
      Asks for help in securing a position in the United States government to help support his motherless children.
    - Benson John Lossing (1813-1891) to J.C. McGuire, administrator of the estate of Dolley Madison 1863 June 16 (Box 3)
      Asks if he can locate among his manuscripts a bill of items for furnishing the White House dated 1811, for use in his book on the War of 1812, The Pictorial Field-Book of the War of 1812]
    - James Madison to Lawrence Taliaferro Dade 1827 July 7, (copy) (Box 3)
      Wants it to be made clear that he attended a celebration in honor of "the deceased Revolutionary Patriot" as a national celebration and not that of a political party.
    - James Madison to George M. Dallas (1792-1864) 1821 June 23, (copy) (Box 3)
      Sends copies of all the correspondence from Alexander James Dallas in his possession, but cannot find one written by Dallas after the British visit in 1814.
    - James Madison to Joseph Delaplaine (1777-1824) 1816-1822, (copy) (Box 3)
      Furnishes very cautious remarks concerning the literary and historical works sent to him for his opinion by Delaplaine, the strongest of which is a suggestion that Mead's School Exercises could use many more illustrations in the work; he also asks to review manuscript papers containing memoranda concerning himself and his career in Repository of the lives and portraits of distinguished American characters by Delaplaine.
    - James Madison to Frederick DePeyster 1832 July 31, (copy) (Box 3)
      Asks DePeyster to thank the New York Historical Society for sending him a copy of The Published Collections of the New York Historical Society and stresses the importance of such work to the preservation of the history of the United States.
    - James Madison to Lyman Copeland Draper (1815-1891), copy 1833 August 9 (Box 3)
      Responds to his request for sources of printed information about his career by directing him to examine the newspapers during his elections, and records of public transactions.
    - James Madison to William Duane (1760-1835) copy 1803 August 20 (Box 3)
      Cautions silence concerning the cession of the Louisiana Territory to the United States, except that Great Britain has not been obstructive in any way.
    - James Madison to Du [Plantier]1805 June 2, (copy) (Box 3)
      Asks his aid in securing the best land for General LaFayette with the land grant from Congress, some of which is in the Louisiana Territory.
    - James Madison to John Murray Forbes (1771-1831) 1824 September 18 (Box 3)
      Introduction of the Rev. Herbert Marshall.
    - James Madison to Isaac Hite 1832 August 24, (copy) (Box 3)
      Refuses to participate in the recommendation of candidates for officers and describes the state of his health.
    - James Madison to Robert Livingston and James Monroe, incomplete (copy) [ca. 1803 July-August] (Box 3)
      Comments on the Convention with France concerning shipping.
    - James Madison, Sr. to James Madison, Jr. 1784 June 10 (Box 3)
      Informs him that John Stanley and George Wilson have entered a caveat against the patent for their 40,000 acres of land, asks him about the tobacco, and about ordering copies of Burrows' Reports.
    - John Marshall (1755-1835) to James M. Marshall 1808 May 20 (Box 3)
      Discusses various legal matters with his brother.
    - James Murray Mason (1798-1871) to Dolley Madison 1837 July 17 (Box 3)
      Introduction of Judge Thomas McKean Pettit (1797-1853).
    - John Mason to James Madison 1802 June 4 (Box 3)
      Letter of introduction for Nicolas King.
    - Ann Maury (1803-1876) to Dolley Madison 1838 February 12 (Box 3)
      Writes of her father, James Maury, and cousin, Matthew F. Maury.
    - Virgil Maxcy (1785-1844), Solicitor of the Treasury, to John Payne Todd 1837 March 25 (Box 3)
      Requests documents identifying the legal representative of James Madison.
    - Virgil Maxcy (1785-1844), Solicitor of the Treasury, to John Payne Todd n.d. (Box 3)
      Thanks her for consenting to construct for her one of Mrs. Madison's "beautiful turbans".
    - Anne Mifflin, Quaker Preacher, to Dolley Madison n.y. June 15 (Box 3)
      Encloses a manuscript (not present) as a subject for her reflection.
    - R.W. Moffat to Dolley Madison 1841 March 14 (Box 3)
      Asks for help in getting his trunk to Richmond.
    - Henry W. Moncure to Dolley Madison 1842 December 17 (Box 3)
      Discusses the sale of Montpelier.
    - James Monroe to Andrew Ellicott 1802 September 10 (Box 3)
      Writes concerning the settlement of the boundary between Tennessee and Virginia, mentioning the work of Joshua Fry and Peter Jefferson which was probably based on astronomical observations.
    - Eliza Orr to James Madison 1801 July 28 (Box 3)
      Defends the character of her husband who did not receive a desired position.
    - Eliza Orr to James Madison n.d. (Box 3)
      Invites Dolley to visit them that evening if she is not too fatigued.
    - Joseph Prentis to James Madison 1801 December 18 (Box 3)
      Letter of introduction for his friend, Dr. [Philip?] Barraud of Norfolk, who may be interested in establishing a hospital for invalid mariners in Washington.
    - William Campbell Preston (1794-1860) to Dolley Madison 1839 February 4, n.d. (Box 3)
      Expresses his admiration of Dolley at length (1839) and invites her to dine (n.d.).
    - David Meade Randolph to James Madison 1828 October 10 (Box 3)
      Seeks his aid in securing a pension from Congress.
    - John Randolph of Roanoke (1773-1833) to James Madison [1803] (Box 3)
      Writes concerning a report in the House of Representatives that four thousand French troops have arrived at New Orleans and asks if Madison has any additional information about the rumor.
    - John Randolph of Roanoke to Mrs. [Fulwar?] Skipwith 1810 June 6 (Box 3)
      Regrets they are unable to visit, thanks her for her care of [John] St. George [Randolph?] (1792-1857), and discusses the account with Dr. Brockenbrough.
    - Thomas Ritchie (1778-1854), editor of Richmond Enquirer, to James Madison and Dolley Madison 1825 December 10, n.d. (Box 3)